<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<rfc ipr="trust200902"
    docName="draft-pfister-homenet-dot-00"
    category="std">

<?rfc toc="yes"?> <?rfc symrefs="yes"?> <?rfc autobreaks="yes"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?> <?rfc compact="yes"?> <?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<front>

<title abbrev="dot homenet">Special Use Top Level Domain '.homenet'</title>

<author initials="P" surname="Pfister" fullname="Pierre Pfister">
<organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street/>
<city>Paris</city>
<country>France</country>
</postal>
<email>pierre.pfister@darou.fr</email>
</address>
</author>

<date month="October" year="2016" />

<keyword>Homenet</keyword>
<keyword>TLD</keyword>
<keyword>RFC6761</keyword>
<keyword>.homenet</keyword>

<abstract>
    <t>This document specifies the behavior that is expected from the Domain Name System with regard to DNS queries for names ending with '.homenet.', and designates this top-level domain as a special-use domain name . The '.homenet' top-level domain intends to replace '.home' which was originally specified in Home Networking Control Protocol (HNCP) as the default domain name for home networks.</t>
</abstract>

</front>
<middle>
    
    
<section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
    <t>Users and devices within a home network require other devices to be identified by names that are unique within the boundaries of the home network <xref target="RFC7368"/>. The naming mechanism also needs to function without configuration from the user. While it is conceivable that this could be done through a delegation from the ISP, homenets must function without that delegation.   A default name with a scope limited to each individual homenet needs to be used.</t>
    
    <t>The '.homenet' top-level domain replaces '.home' which was specified in <xref target="RFC7788"/> as the default domain-name for home networks. '.home' would certainly be the most user-friendly option, but evidence indicates that '.home' queries frequently leak out and reach the root name servers <xref target="ICANN1"/> <xref target="ICANN2"/>. As a result, the use of '.home' has been deprecated; this document updates <xref target="RFC7788"/> to replace '.home' with '.homenet', while another document, <xref target="I-D.ietf-homenet-redact"/> deprecates the use of the '.home' TLD.</t>

    <t>This document registers the top-level domain '.homenet.' as a special-use domain name <xref target="RFC6761"/> and specifies the behavior that is expected from the Domain Name System with regard to DNS queries for names whose rightmost non-terminal label is 'homenet'.  Queries for names ending with '.homenet.' are of local significance within the scope of a home network, meaning that identical queries will result in different results from one home network to another.   In other words, a name ending in '.homenet' is not globally unique.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="guidance" title="General Guidance">
    <t>The top-level domain name '.homenet.' is to be used for naming within a home network. Names ending with '.homenet.' MUST refer to services that are located within a home network (e.g., a printer, or a toaster).</t>
    <t>DNS queries for names ending with '.homenet.' are resolved using local resolvers on the homenet.   Such queries MUST NOT be recursively forwarded to servers outside the scope of the home network.</t>
    <t>Although home networks most often provide one or more service discovery mechanisms, it is still expected that some users will see, remember, and sometimes even type, names ending with '.homenet'. It is therefore desireable that users identify the top-level domain and understand that using it expresses the intention to connect to a service that is specific to the home network to which they are connected.  Enforcing the fulfillment of this intention is out of scope for this document.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="considerations" title="Domain Name Reservation Considerations">
    <t>This section defines the behavior of systems involved in domain name resolution when serving queries for names ending with '.homenet.' (as per <xref target="RFC6761"/>).

        <list style="numbers">
            <!-- Users -->
            <t>Users can use names ending with '.homenet.' just as they would any other domain name. The '.homenet' name is chosen to be readily recognized by users as signifying that the name is addressing a service on the homenet to which the user's device is connected.</t>

            <!-- Application Software -->
            <!-- <t>Applications MUST NOT treat domain names ending with '.homenet.' specially with respect to the resolution protocol used.</t> -->

            <!-- Name Resolution APIs and Libraries -->
            <t>Name resolution APIs and libraries MUST NOT recognize names ending with '.homenet.' as special and MUST NOT treat them differently. Name resolution APIs MUST send queries for such names to their configured caching DNS server(s). Using a caching server other than the server or servers offered by the home network will result in failure to correctly resolve queries for '.homenet'.</t>

            <!-- Caching DNS Servers -->
            <t>Unless configured otherwise, Caching DNS servers MUST behave as described in Locally Served Zones <xref target="RFC6303"/> Section 3. Caching DNS Servers that are part of a home network MAY be configured manually or automatically (e.g., for auto-configuration purposes) to act differently, e.g., by querying another name server configured as authoritative for part of the domain, or proxying the request through a different mechanism.</t>

            <!-- Authoritative DNS Servers -->
            <t>Authoritative DNS Servers SHOULD recognize such names as special-use and SHOULD NOT, by default, attempt to look up NS records for these names. Servers that are part of a home network or providing name resolution services for a home network MAY be configured to act as authoritative for the whole top-level domain or a part of it.</t>

            <!-- DNS Server Operators: -->
            <!-- <t>DNS server operators MUST NOT attempt to configure DNS servers to act as authoritative for any of these names.  [[ TODO - AS112 delegation ]] </t> -->

            <!-- DNS Registries/Registrars: -->
            <t>DNS Registries/Registrars MUST NOT grant requests to register '.homenet' in the normal way to any person or entity.  '.homenet' is registered in perpetuity to IANA:</t>
            <artwork>
        Domain Name: HOMENET
        Registrar: RESERVED-INTERNET ASSIGNED NUMBERS AUTHORITY
        Whois Server: whois.iana.org
        Referral URL: http://res-dom.iana.org
        Name Server: A.IANA-SERVERS.NET
        Name Server: B.IANA-SERVERS.NET
        Status: clientDeleteProhibited
        Status: clientTransferProhibited
        Status: clientUpdateProhibited</artwork>
        </list>
    </t>
</section>

<section title="Updates to Home Networking Control Protocol">
    <t>The final paragraph of Homenet Considerations Protocol <xref target="RFC7788"/>, section 8, is updated as follows:</t>
    <t>OLD:<list style="empty">
        <t>Names and unqualified zones are used in an HNCP network to provide naming and service discovery with local significance.  A network-wide zone is appended to all single labels or unqualified zones in order to qualify them. ".home" is the default; however, an administrator MAY configure the announcement of a Domain-Name TLV (Section 10.6) for the network to use a different one.  In case multiple are announced, the domain of the node with the greatest node identifier takes precedence.</t>
        </list>
        NEW: <list style="empty">
            <t>Names and unqualified zones are used in an HNCP network to provide naming and service discovery with local significance.  A network-wide zone is appended to all single labels or unqualified zones in order to qualify them. ".homenet" is the default; however, an administrator MAY configure the announcement of a Domain-Name TLV (Section 10.6) for the network to use a different one.  In case multiple are announced, the domain of the node with the greatest node identifier takes precedence.</t>
            <t>The '.homenet' special-use name does not require a special resolution protocol.  Names for which the rightmost non-terminal label is 'homenet' are resolved using the DNS protocol <xref target="RFC1035"/>.  The handling of these names is specified in <xref target="I-D.ietf-homenet-dot"/>.
        </list></t>
    </section>

<section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
    <t>Although a DNS record returned as a response to a query ending with '.homenet.' is expected to have local significance and be returned by a server involved in name resolution for the home network the device is connected in, such response MUST NOT be considered more trustworthy than would be a similar response for any other DNS query.</t>
    <t>Because '.homenet' is not globally scoped and cannot be secured using DNSSEC based on the root domain's trust anchor, there is no way to tell, using a standard DNS query, in which home network scope an answer belongs. Consequently, users may experience surprising results with such names when roaming to different home networks.   To prevent this from happening, it may be useful for the resolver to identify different home networks on which it has resolved names, but this is out of scope for this document.</t>
</section>

<section title="IANA Considerations">
    <t>IANA is requested to record the top-level domain ".homenet" in the Special-Use Domain Names registry [SUDN].</t>
    <t>IANA is reminded that an insecure delegation for these zones is required for compliance with <xref target="RFC6303"/> to break the DNSSEC chain of trust.</t>
</section>

<section title="Acknowledgments">
    <t>The author would like to thank Stuart Cheshire for his prior work on '.home', as well as the homenet chairs: Mark Townsley and Ray Bellis.</t>
</section>

</middle>

<back>

<references title="Normative References">
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6303.xml"?>
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6761.xml"?>
  <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-homenet-redact"?>
</references>

<references title="Informative References">
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1035.xml"?>
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7368.xml"?>
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7788.xml"?>
  <?rfc include="I-D.ietf-homenet-dot"?>
  <reference anchor="ICANN1" target="https://www.icann.org/en/system/files/files/resolutions-new-gtld-annex-1-07oct13-en.pdf">
      <front>
          <title>New gTLD Collision Risk Mitigation</title>
          <author/>
          <date month="October" year="2013" />
      </front>
  </reference>
  <reference anchor="ICANN2" target="https://www.icann.org/en/system/files/files/resolutions-new-gtld-annex-1-07oct13-en.pdf">
      <front>
          <title>New gTLD Collision Occurence Management</title>
          <author/>
          <date month="October" year="2013" />
      </front>
  </reference>
  <reference anchor="SUDN" target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/special-use-domain-names/special-use-domain-names.xhtml">
      <front>
          <title>Special-Use Domain Names Registry</title>
          <author/>
          <date month="July" year="2012" />
      </front>
  </reference>
</references>

</back>
</rfc>
